do this interview and help me get my
thoughts down like I said I'm better at
doing this in a conversation so why are
we creating it's good so I have this
idea for a technology cooperative a lot
of it comes from the fact that
technology right now in our lives is so
powerful before this point in history we
weren't able to be doing what I it is I
want to do so technology connects us
like we've never been connected before
it also informs us somewhat
problematically but we do get a lot of
information our fingertips on the
Internet and it makes a lot of things
possible that would have never been
possible before so it has a great impact
on our lives but currently technology is
owned by mainly for companies at least
the technology I'm talking about Amazon
Google Facebook and Apple and they have
a lot of money and a lot of power and
they gain more and more as the months
and years go by as they both create
their own products and amalgamate you
know buy other people's products so what
I propose is we create a tech co-op
especially a user slash platform
cooperative that is like the Netflix of
apps that we run together with liquid
democracy and complete transparency we
use it to create the tools that connect
us and inform us and meet our basic
needs as well as basically everything we
desire it doesn't hand you what you
desire but it gives you the tools to
empower yourself to co-create solutions
so everything in the tech cooperative is
voluntary it's all about empowering the
individual with their own freedom but
like collectively we're able to wield
our power on behalf of every single one
of us so you don't have to create an app
for yourself
we are creating it together but nor do
you have to use it and you can have a
say in what features is created so the
idea is to adjust to this but empower to
create a world that works for you you're
given the tools to do that whether
that's finding the group's finding that
the projects to work on or just saying
this is what's not working for me
and being
with other people to co-create as
leukemic back together we the other
piece is that we're able to do it better
than those four companies I just
mentioned can do because they have to do
it in secrecy or they have to do it in
opposition to the other user they're not
doing it for their user they're doing it
to make money so we have more trust
built into our model we have more
efficiency built into our model and we
design for diversity we're not designing
for the 90% we're designing for
everybody which means designing for the
fringes and the word here that I can't
read without liar the outlier of all
diversity so what I imagine when we have
the Netflix of apps and everything we
need to create as creator or at least
like let's say a dozen tools that
unlocks humanity is that we unlock
humanity we get all of humanity's genius
now we don't get to like co-op people
who don't want to be part of it but we
get to when we release people from the
monotony of their day-to-day lives of
having to go to a job to put food on the
table and having to go to a job
different a roof over their head we get
to unleash their genius and we get all
of the innovation that comes from that
so that is good the Netflix app says go
well that's that's very exciting as the
way that you land out there but I'm
curious how do we get there what's the
start of that process and then how does
that sort of unfold at least in your
current plans of this so that is a big
piece of what I've been working on is
you know like I said there's these
dozens of ideas but how do we in order
for like one to be created one has to
exist like in order for me to be able to
create it I need the thing that helps me
create a team and the thing that helps
you run a team because I can't do it by
myself
so how I see it starting is our first
project is the idea Cafe which is going
to be a platform design and it's going
to be a social media platform design for
humanity to have a real conversation on
from those conversations we're going to
be creating ideas we're gonna get you
can't help but have ideas come out of
conversations it may be we're not able
to move forward on those ideas because
we don't have the
tools to do it but then we're having
those conversations about what tool
would help us do that we just created
you know over the last few months dozens
of ideas but none of them you know there
wasn't organic groups that forms and
made these things magically and so we're
looking at having people be able to
voice what would empower them to do the
work right what would empower them to
well I'm just I can't find a group on my
own I need people to come and be part of
it right so that would be a tool how do
you find a group of people to co-create
with how do you create in a larger group
and so I have a lot of ideas on contest
to be run and ways to to work through an
app creation as a whole that but all of
the ideas that I've created are going to
be more powerful when they come from
organically from us having conversations
because then we have the passion behind
it right like people want to co-create
something that they helped co-create but
they like really yes let's let's figure
out what's going wrong and create it
together
so the idea Cafe will be a space for
anyone to come and discuss world events
discuss problems discuss anything that
would spark a solution and then from
those conversations we're creating the
tools to make it all possible
Cocco so just in terms of the social
media platform itself how would you
distinguish it from other social media
platforms in terms of functionality and
you know features anything like that
because we have had a conversation about
this previously and you said that there
was a different way that the site was
going to be centered rather than
text-based I think you were saying it
was gonna be more video based and video
absorb yes so the idea is the simple
version is you come on there's one
question a day when we start and you get
to be matched up in your what's the word
like your schedule when you're free you
are matched up with two to three other
people to have a conversation around a
meaningful question and together we're
gonna be generating what those questions
are to powerfully move us forward as we
grow we can go from having one question
today that's going to be maybe not spark
everyone's interest to having more than
East quad in each these questions having
one that's focuses on climate change or
poverty reduction or food creation and
whatever it is that you want to be
empowered to co-create with other people
that's where you want to have those
conversations so the idea is everyone
has an account and they say when they're
available they say what they care about
and we match them up to have a
conversation they don't just have one
conversation the idea is hopefully they
have multiple conversations so that the
larger group is able to have a
conversation because if we're talking
with four different people and then we
all go to spur stand talk with the new
four people and go to first and talk
with the new four people the larger
group is able to have a conversation I
think a lot of social media right now
first of all is set up for profit which
means they have a very different
incentive part of which is they make
money off of debate they make money off
of division it keeps us on there longer
they make money off of our addiction and
we can create something that gives us
real connection and empowers us to just
meet with our fellow humans face to face
and see that there are good people
mostly that they're intelligent people
mostly and the ones that we don't get
along with we'll find someone else to
get along with like we can create a
space that brings humanity together for
a conversation and none of them are
doing that there's like I said existing
for profit we don't own them so we can't
say what's not working about them and we
can't work to improve them we can tell
them they can choose to act on it or not
but they're not there to make it a more
better experience for us they're there
to make it a better experience for the
total enough that we give them that they
get money yeah and we have been using
zome and we've got a Facebook group and
things like that and we've had some
really interesting conversations sort of
coming together as large groups and then
splitting off into smaller bubbles and
having discussions around there and it's
working really good you know it's
exciting the things that we've been
talking about and this is sort of a
product from this so if there was a
social media platform that was
specifically designed around these sorts
of things I would definitely be
interested in jumping on board and
hopefully generating some solutions
because we live in pretty strange time
at the moment and so you know I think
more cohesion less division least people
making money off of our division I think
would be a very good thing okay so I'll
go on to some of the criticisms of just
cooperatives and social media platforms
yeah yeah well unfortunately we live in
a pretty difficult world there's a lot
of competition and saturation things
like that but yeah did a bit of research
just to see sort of hat wire coops fail
and one of them would be how do you
incentivize people to do the work that
is required so how do you get the people
because you're not a tech person
yourself but you're hoping to attract
and tick people and bring them in so how
will you incentivize those B so the
people doing the tech work the people
people are having the conversations that
spark the ideas aren't getting paid
that's payment in and of itself it ought
to be part of that being able to
co-create together however when
someone's full-time job is coding or
doing the graphics or doing that piece
of it they're going to get paid and so
we are incentivizing them in the regular
way we're also asking though
with everything we have with labor like
not just for our cooperative but also
when we create a labor platform
what can incentivize you beyond money
right what makes your life better that
isn't increasing your paycheck because
if we increase your paycheck we have to
increase everyone's paycheck whereas if
we create a healthcare system for you
that your pain into like everyone can
pay into then everybody gets that if
we're creating a way for you to eat
organic food that you have to put lace
labor into everybody that's that so we
are looking for ways to solve the the
incentivization problem for everybody
I'm like how do we get you more of what
you need to do right if your house gets
cleaned you can spend more time on tech
if you're if you're a coder I don't have
that skill but I might be able to clean
house so to begin with it might be quite
difficult just because like we're where
is that money coming from it's not like
you've got you know billion
is investing in it or anything at this
point in time that's around getting sort
of the initial payments going and sort
of previously like months and months ago
was the idea of the Netflix of app so
the idea is we're paying into a pool and
then voting on where that money goes
which means people are putting ten
dollars a month into that money and that
is depending on our Thresh our are
starting threshold a lot of money to
work with like if you have ten thousand
people each putting in ten dollars a
month that's a hundred thousand dollars
a month to work and create apps with
however we have nothing to offer them so
they're not putting in ten dollars a
month
they'd be putting in like a crowdfunding
campaign where they're putting in just
ten dollars and we're using that hundred
thousand to create our first project
that in this case isn't the idea Cafe
because I don't think people would pay
for the idea cafe it doesn't give them a
in a regular game a solution right it's
not making life easier it's it is but
like it's not regular life easier it's
not getting them more food for cheaper
those those incentives one of which
could be to create the labor platform
because the labor platform that helps us
you know we create the uber the
TaskRabbit all of that that we
collectively owned together we create it
so it's not for profit so more money's
going between the transaction with a
tiny percentage going to create the
platform we can vote on what a tax is we
can vote on what that platform money is
and that can be used to create all of
the tech but I do think matter to have a
$10 a month fee that we all say because
then we're also knowing the people that
are pretty pain into other people who
won't care about it people who see the
vision and want to co-create a global
tech weapon yep so you would start with
something like err Tasker or something
that's connect individuals to get you
jobs and working things like start with
one of the ideas that is a money
generator it isn't and so something that
offers value to people and a percentage
goes into the pool so that you're we
need money we need money to create web
so there has to be a way to make the
money either it's you know there's
enough of us that it's it's by donation
we have yes everyone puts any $10 I like
that because I think it's more fair I
think it's more we all have an equal
payment in and we therefore all have an
equal voice yeah okay well there are
already a few sites that exist social
media sites that I don't think they have
quite the grand vision that you have
outlined but a lot of them are trying to
move away from because our information
is sort of collected and sold and we
there's not much transparency around
what's happening for them so yeah places
like a diaspora sorry I Oh mind
these places are all kind of a lot of
them use blockchain as well as part of
the technology to try to decentralize it
and give users more control why not can
it connect with those people and try to
team up with them instead of trying to
build something from the ground up
there's a few things in which I do think
we need to start from the ground up
there needs to be enough people
co-creating it together and it's created
openly and transparently that anyone who
comes on board can see how we got there
if somebody was doing something amazing
and was willing to have me on board I
would absolutely go be part of that as
long as there was a certain amount of
foundation like we're all gonna own it
together not us gonna own it together
and then sell it to everybody else but
we are gonna own it together humanity is
gonna own it together or whoever would
never members choose to opt in I need it
to be democratic or have something that
is better than democracy and
transparency nearly complete
transparency I don't want decisions
being made free behind closed doors that
I don't get to be privy to and so the
other option is although they yes you
own your data a lot of times that means
they don't want to share it that means
you don't I mean like what we do on
Facebook what we do on Amazon what we do
on Google we are the the commodity hmm
it's our data there's so many more
powerful things we could be using our
data for than selling us more crap or
rigging elections or you know what I
mean that that kind of thing we can be
using our data to cure cancer to make
our lives better to do and so having
systems that uses our data voluntarily
and
safely so you can opt into it I don't
think is what they're trying to create
they're trying to create keep your data
to yourself right and so there's a lot
of benefit a lot of the powerful tools
are created because we're sharing data
before sharing data on what our
purchases are we can create the entire
chain of production when it makes sense
to do so it's like hey you're all buying
toilet paper we probably knew that
without some data you know what point
does it make sense to have our own
toilet paper well what do we need to
have in that function how you know how
how many do we need like how many toilet
paper factories and when does it make
sense to have one in your area using our
data helps us I want to say centrally
planned not centrally planned it is
dispersed planning but like we are
putting into the system we're only gonna
put our data into the system if we gain
something right away and we can see
where it's used and hopefully we can
pull it back if it doesn't hurt the
whole if we want to yeah so in the first
conversation that we had about this you
did sort of talk because this is sort of
more the tech side but how do you
imagine it works when you've actually
got people in real life I think you said
that you probably have communities of
people living together in sort of cells
around the Dunbar number do you want to
sort of flesh out some of those ideas I
had I mean I live in community with with
people and it does functionally well at
the 50 or 60 people that are there
working with um conflict resolution and
whatnot but there's no guarantee you're
gonna be able to find a community right
now in in the world it's like we'll go
and create a community and sustain like
from the ground up just grow your own
food and do that's not sustainable for a
lot of people because they can't even
sign that let alone run it and so the
idea with the Dunbar number that we were
talking about I think was that like if
you can make 150 connections that are
meaningful the old-school way which I
think with the Dunbar number is is that
that's like a tribe that's like a group
of people who all know each other they
know the connections they know we can
create something that is more connected
because maybe my Dunbar number is like
50 people I go to church with and 50
people I eat in community with and 50
people I'm working
tech projects with I'm interconnected to
150 and all of those people are
interconnected to their own different
different groups so we have like a
global connection that is vinegar and
yet we don't need to have more than you
know what our brains and and hearts and
souls can handle as far as as far as
connection I do think we will be living
in community and those will be the
groups were making negotiation impacts
with right like this is what it is to be
part of this community there'll be
something bigger this is what it means
to be part of this app community right
you're part of the food community you
get to choose which one you're part of
and that smaller group makes more rules
over each other in a way that you pick
which one you're part of right this one
says you're doing 30 hours a week and
you're all eating organic and it's vegan
this one says it's 10 hours a week most
things are robotically done and you know
like you get to choose which one you're
part of as long as they also want you
and if nobody wants you you're giving
the tools to co-create one that you want
it create with other people yeah Coco so
what is the sort of broader philosophy
behind this like what's the point in
coming up with this tea platform other
than the fact that they're sort of
selling our data and we're not really
sure what they're doing and you know
we're having all these conflicts online
what what are sort of the overall goals
that you're hoping to achieve I want
access to these tools I don't want I
want to access to the tools we're gonna
create together I want to be able to eat
better and not have to do the the mental
work and have it cost so much and have
it I want to be able to connect with
community when I want to connect with it
I want to be able to find activity
partners and I want to be able to save
our planet from the destruction it's
heading towards and be able to harness
our power in our political system
together and be able to have information
that we can trust and actually use
instead of having it yeah we have all of
information or fingertips but is it
useful is it trust word can we use it to
have a conversation I could do all of
the research I want on a topic I still
to talk to somebody who doesn't have
access to that research we can make a
foundation
we've already had the conversation what
do we trust how do we make it usable so
that yes just give me people who don't
trust it and don't want to use it but
we've decided we want to trust it use it
and created it for that purpose hmm okay
just all selfish I want to have access
to like humanity's genius I want a cure
for cancer
I want like all of my goods and services
available at cost I want to be able to
like spend my life plane and in doing
what I enjoy and I want everybody else
to have that too
I want to like I want to vote for my kid
that works that isn't it is the Omni win
we're like we're co-creating a better
future instead of this like constant
pitted against each other this yeah well
I guess because the thing is there are a
lot of these things that are already out
there like it Oscar exists
uber already exists all of the all of
these things are sort of in the
marketplace no you don't know own it but
you don't need to in order for enrich
your life and be useful as right now
TaskRabbit and uber are not paying their
employed they're not paying their
contract workers they're not paying
their drivers well we also aren't able
to co-create and sorry for interrupting
we're also not able to co-create
solutions to get there that work beyond
what uber ubers like one platform
they're like you hire a driver if you
can't afford it too bad this isn't the
site for you if we're able to co-create
it together I'm able to have a
conversation like hey you know what I'm
really not able to afford new per driver
but the uber driver should make be able
to make money we can create a system
where the uber driver makes more money
than they're making on uber and it costs
me less hmm because we can car share
right like if I'm coming back from a
event and I don't want to take the bus
and it says hey again sharing your data
there's four other people in your
neighborhood if you all paid chip in
that's 15 bucks to get home it's gonna
be delivered right to your door but the
uber driver gets $60 whereas they would
have maybe gotten 20 from over and we
wouldn't call it over clearly that's a
proprietary name but our version of our
version you know that if we don't feel
safe with certain drivers as I know
there's a lyft that is is
was women-only now it's like we can
choose drivers that we feel safe with we
can we can have more while what does the
word rating systems that we've
co-created together so they're not this
you know hard to pull down it's like as
a driver how do you feel safe as a
passenger how do you feel safe how do we
have both people at the table having
that conversation we can make all of the
things better when we own them together
where we can't we can't make over better
you know they're doing honey for a chair
holders it's not there to make the
drivers lives better
it's life better enough that we give
them our money yeah yeah yeah I mean
there is there is an incentive for those
companies to you know improve on the
model and make sure there's not you know
violence happening within the the cab
and making sure they register the people
and all those kinds of things but I
guess the the the trouble that I can see
is just growing to the point where you
can compete with those things because
part part of the reason why Buber works
so well is because it's quite
distributed like there are a lot of
people who are already using the app and
so that gives you quite large coverage
like how do you you know you can reason
these we don't create anything until we
have the threshold of people to create
it with we don't create over with you
and then we're like hey do you guys want
over we ask we're like hey Vancouver hey
Toronto hey New York how many of you
want a cooperative ride-sharing app you
know and like you're not launching anis
in first of all by the time we create it
it's already exists and we can launch in
every city but to create it we need
enough riders and passengers in one city
for that to be for that to be usable so
what do we want it to look like I think
that if there was a cooperative
ride-sharing app it would take over from
uber overnight because it solves a lot
of their problems but not if it's
designed in secret
not if it's designed with again four of
us created in going like it's
cooperative like the drivers could have
a say and it just runs like every other
cooperative which is awesome but run
like a secret corporation run behind in
boardrooms behind closed doors yeah yeah
I'm definitely against the secrecy as
well so
you did briefly mentioned sort of Omni
when and nonrival for us and those are
some of the ideas that have been
throwing or been thrown around the
community that we are we met each other
through so do you want to explore that a
little bit just like moving away from
rival Ross dynamics and the idea of a
system where every new person if you're
a new driver to bur you're costing the
old drivers something right now they
have less fares to share around I don't
know if Albert rideshare is gonna solve
that problem but when you don't need to
work because your food system is created
and you're like Oh more driver is
awesome we don't you know that just
means I don't feel the need that there
was 20 hours of work that people needed
and now I feel like there's 15 hours of
work that people needed when it's the
opposite dynamic where I'm not that's
not going to explain it okay that every
person who comes to the table brings
with them their data brings with them
their their their brain brings with them
their passion and their connections and
so every new person isn't competition
their cooperation so it's designed into
the system that like yes bring your data
yes come on board we want to make it
work we don't want to cut this off at
ten thousand be like we're gonna make a
really awesome way for just us the more
people who are there the better it is
the more people that are to create new
apps the more people that are to pay for
those apps the more people there are to
bring their data to make it more rich
and to be able to make the toilet paper
factories there was also well I mean
we're also because I guess part of the
game be faced is to move away from the
sort of unsustainability of the water
world because at the moment we're just
we're consuming too many resources just
the competitive nature of capitalism is
pretty dangerous for all of us but how
would you know if we're recreating all
of these services and products how do we
how is that different from just
capitalism but you know a cooperative
version of that because we're still
gonna expend a lot of resources and
presumably more it spreads to other
we design or the planet I mean we
designed like right now we have cell
phones that are designed to be thrown
out in two to three years their minds
their you don't like they're not
designed to just switch out the screen
to just or a switch out they want you to
throw it out we don't want to throw it
out we have a different incentive as a
user cooperative we want a lasting
product we want something and so we're
and hopefully we're designing it so that
it can be broken back down to its
components and reuse we don't have to
mine as often as we are we're designing
it with us in mind we want something
that lasts we want something that's that
uses as little resources as possible
including labor and the actual physical
resources that's not what they're
incentivized to do they're incentivized
to create a cheap product that will let
them get away with mmm yeah so so it's
really kind of the whole thing is
hopefully once once it starts building
and taking off the idea is to sort of
get everybody on the same page with the
project of the co-operative and try to
get everybody to understand some of the
issues that we need to face and the ways
that we need to address them so just
like capitalism we're all acting in our
own best interests and somehow magically
that makes is supposed to make a better
world but it also makes a very
destructive world where we're in
competition with each other and we've
incentivize sociopaths and people who
want to game the system for their own
benefit we can create in the way where
you still get a say in what you want if
you want a different cellphone if you
want a blackberry if you want you know I
mean whatever functions are for yours
that doesn't know you don't get like
there's gonna be a cost to that if you
have your own individual no one else
wants it yours is gonna cost more either
in money or labor and something that
we've used as an unit of exchange but
there's going to also be an incentive to
have one right like so they'll probably
be one that is very universal and the
niche ones but together we want to
create a system and a company that
doesn't cannibalize off itself right
like if you want to come in and create a
competing to telephone company or
competing toilet paper factory why like
why would you want to do that unless
it's it's meeting a need that you don't
have right like if we have white toilet
paper and you want blue toilet paper why
I don't know but like then come and help
us create blue toilet paper you know
like we don't need to have you create
your own system and your own delivery
system like the point is is if what we
are creating isn't meeting your
individual needs
come help us meet your individual needs
without you needing to go and recreate
the system again and again and again
which is what capitalism does so it
competes so we get the best price in the
market but there's so much inefficiency
there but they're all kind of lysing off
each other they're all like it just
doesn't work and it's destroying our
planet there are just incentivize to get
cell phones to throw away so they can
stay in business we don't need to create
consumers so that we can sell a million
in cell phones a year we need enough
cell phone to meet people's needs those
are different incentives right we need
to make enough of them so everyone has
one and enough components so we can keep
making it better like keep replacing
that he says yes the difficulty there is
that the people who are designing these
phones that they cut that's the
labelling that there's that they keep
designing new phones so what do people
do as jobs and this new sort of tick
hole
can people just say yeah like it's very
much based on like a resource-based
economy where like do we need people
designing new phones
uh not really yeah we have a pretty
family but people are gonna want to
because that's fun creating something
new and better is amazing and so they're
going to create it it's gonna be doing
better and so if you're somebody who
wants things right away we'll have a
system decide who gets those things
first like the people who made them
clearly get them first right you're the
one who created and then how do you get
them to the next person the next group
of people I don't need the newest phone
I like my old one other people it's
gonna be a bigger incentive for them to
need the newer one right away if it's
gonna bring you more happiness do you
get it right away okay maybe you don't
get the next new one
though I don't know like whatever it's
gonna bring us the most happiness the
point is to listen to people not
everyone's gonna be happy all the time
there's a saying in my community which
is like mo that most of most of the time
mmm and oh you don't get to be the
supreme ruler of the world and could be
a billionaire who gets everything handed
to you and you don't get objecting you
get you know like not even in-between
you get what honestly a billionaire
today can't get because we're I'm sure
gonna cure cancer in a way that like
that's not happening tomorrow it's like
you know a decade two decades away and
when I say sure I mean again most people
get most of what they want most of the
time most cancer isn't created and most
cancer that is created is cured on a
level that we would assume is cured
considering today's standards and I say
Bill Gates wrong person Steve Jobs the
Koch brothers they died of cancer
they're billionaires they couldn't buy
that there's going to be a higher
standard of living that we all get based
on the innovation that we we
collectively unleash yeah because I
guess one of the problems within the
scientific community is they kind of
incentivize to never solve the problems
because once they've solved the problems
that our funding anymore and if that's
what you specialize them so but the
incentives are all wrong yeah yeah so
yeah money as an incentive breaks
everything if you're playing a sport
because you're making money you're not
playing to be the best of your sport if
you are million people because you're
making money you're not playing you're
not playing you know medicine in order
to get better at science if you're doing
that is if you're doing science in order
to get the next grants you're not doing
it to get that Eureka moment which is
what we want scientists to get to like
what would make it better for you is
only money because what money represents
on our planet when people have all of
their needs met they choose to put their
labor and put their genius and passion
where they want to and that's where we
want people doing it well I think some
people I think some people are just
motivated by money and I think you'd
need money or some kind of currency to
transact in the system anyway and I
think money is actually one of the
interesting
to look at in terms of how we change the
incentives of the system because if you
change how money works you change how
people behave because at the moment
money is a scarce resource so everyone's
sort of competing for it in a non zero
in a zero-sum fashion but there are some
ideas out like the adjustable universal
basic income which alex Howlett tools
talking about we are basically the
government prints as much money as they
need to in order to make sure that these
people money for people to spend so it's
less competitive for just getting money
in the first place because so long as
people have money to spend the economy
can keep taking over so and I think that
people have mentioned hollow chain to
you of a few a few times
so those some of the technologies that
might be implemented in the system just
to give people something to show that
they have value for this and then there
would be I think again incentivizing for
like even technology if you're creating
technology to make profit you're not
creating the best technology you're not
creating to innovate however there is
this certain we live in a world that
needs money and so if what is going to
incentivize the masses is to create a
currency we will create a currency
together or though right it's not going
to be one of the crypto currencies
that's already out there how many are
there now that was intenta one of those
isn't mad our new American dollar but a
million of us a billion of us being like
hey what are the features the best
crypto currencies and what how are they
created how do we create ours I mean I
think common planet has a really cool
idea for how to create a currency and
maybe we would cream that like where
you're creating it by doing the labor
and get it once you spend it nobody gets
it and so it's a it's a it's a non
recycle it's a nun you use it up so it
doesn't go yeah so it doesn't accumulate
yes similar to what our Renzi was
talking about was that project yeah okay
yeah I thought that was a really cool
idea really really interesting
definitely
don't agree with but like I would
absolutely do that over what we're
currently doing and I feel thing about
basically everyone's idea moving forward
I'm like two ice Nazi I see some holes
in it I'm sure like people see mine and
also infinitely better than what we
currently have yeah well yeah well the
purpose is to just get to a better place
because the thing is we live in very
wealthy countries and we have all of
these technologies and all of this all
of these reasons or says but it's a very
unhappy place to be and it's just it
just seems insane and in so many ways
because you know eating up our resources
and creating all of this cultural
conflict it's just yes no no we're
really disconnected like even really
rich people are unhappy yes some of the
most happy people are probably those
that aren't rich and don't get their
value from from having currency we can
create a better world by constantly
asking what would help you yeah what
would help you live a better life yeah
because at the moment I think the world
is kind of just a giant casino because
everyone's trying to do whatever it is
that maximizes their short-term pleasure
and that just doesn't make you happy
like the things that make people happy
are having community happy having their
loved ones around them having a sense of
purpose and things like that and the
model that we're working with at the
moment just doesn't do that actually
community is a takeaway from my
connection in anything it adds to it you
know you having a food doesn't take away
for mine unless there's only a finite
amount of food and we can create enough
food no problem right now on this planet
we create enough food yeah but we saw
our yeah we you know we we have enough
land to grow communities and shelter on
as long as people aren't having 15
houses that they're not even rent you
know like we have enough we just don't
have a way to get it to everyone
the previous solution to that was
communism and it clearly was about a
solution to that but we can create a
solution to that because it cuz
we're not central planning we're
literally using data on a plan and
looking at like what's going wrong and
recreating it to like we're not ignoring
that things could go wrong we're looking
for things to go wrong and fixing them
and then new things will go wrong and
we'll fix that we never get to
perfection we're just always looking for
what is the next iteration that makes
this better and we also really suck at
handing back power once we have it so
we're never gonna centralize power we're
just gonna as much as possible I'm gonna
be like right this is a tech company and
only a tech company so even if there's a
board of directors has some amount of
power which I've just in my head
designed to be as little as possible
it's still only a tech company it's not
making laws for you to follow
it's like want to use this service is it
not working for you how can we make it
better not like you must use it you must
give us your data unless we collectively
somehow decide something is so
fundamentally important we need your
data on it but you get a say in that
and even then I will fight against that
even if I want to give my dad I want it
to be voluntary every single time yes
well about that that was one of my key
questions is avoiding power
centralization because you know you can
always start off with the best of
intentions but once people see an
opportunity to exploit a system often
those people will find their way into
the halls of power and then they'll
start you know centralizing things and
then that's really why communism failed
is because you know that the idea was to
screen everything out that you you had
this pool of people who were in the
middle and they forced everyone out and
they took advantage of that situation so
have you have you thought much about how
you would you know stop that from
happening
well you see there's gonna be a board of
directors are they gonna be permanent
permanently fixed in those positions or
is it gonna be a rotating it's a it's
how I envisioned it being and it might
need to be a longer time period between
elections but every year the talk the
people with the top delegated votes
becomes the board of directors and they
work together so let's say yeah I don't
even know how many board of directors we
need but I'm gonna say five maybe ten so
it's intense it's a fun number there's
Ted Kord of directors so
that doesn't mean they have equals say
around that table because we're
delegating our vote to them based on
like with democracy so if at any end its
streams lives you're able to see what is
going on you don't have to watch it cuz
who wants to watch that but enough
people will be watching and that you can
transfer your vote so if you imagine if
the president did something to piss off
50% of the population it just moved and
there's a new president like it's like
you could have someone at that table has
99 percent of the vote and you have
someone who got elected and now is zero
percent of the vote they're just getting
paid for that year ya get reelected next
year but so what
they're you know they're there to be
devil's advocate they're there to be
something to be like always the
dissenting vote the issue would be if
all of those people work together and
together they're deciding on shitty
things right and then like what you
can't transfer your vote to anyone so we
have a recall for election when we see
that's happening it's like enough of us
just pull out our power and be like ah
re-election right we don't want to do
that too often but if that's what's
happening and they're now buddy-buddy
and they're working in cohesion against
us yeah other is they're not really
worried and we're only empowering a
group of people if we need to if we need
a smaller group of people to be able to
meet and move a company forward let's do
it if it's gonna make better products
and make us get to where we're going but
again they're not deciding on who we get
to marry they don't deciding what's
legal and illegal they're just like hey
there's where here's the projects and
we're not even assigned to much projects
to fund we are deciding on which
projects to fund it's lit I don't even
know what they do because I'm not a like
how do we move this forward to be great
to have that now to create the idea cafe
and create you know the labor platform
create something to say how do we fund
it what is illegal what's what is the
what what do we need to know legally
what do we need you know pretty much to
do the work that they expect one
entrepreneur to do and it's not
happening because I don't want to be an
entrepreneur I want to be in a co-op
yeah yeah fair enough
well hopefully you've got enough
entrepreneurial Ness about yourself to
actually get this thing started because
yeah that meant I was thinking while you
were saying that maybe it's worth coming
up with like a constitution of
the cooperative so this kind of some
fundamental things that we're all
agreeing on when we when we're buying
into this so that we can try to avoid
some of those you know conflicts and
changes of policy because yeah you know
people people can change the rules
partway through if they have the power
to change those rules so if there was a
constitutional would be a bit more solid
and just a few fundamental things we're
usually you couldn't pull those labels
livers because we've all agreed that we
will absolutely have that I'm not going
to create that both because I don't want
right back writing that out sounds very
horrible to me also I want to be part of
the conversations that create that right
I want to be able to be like what are
our values what are the things we want
to that Constitution what do we do with
sociopaths what do we do with people who
game the system and I don't think it's
if we literally just create it in a way
where they're not incentivized to work
for theirselves in isolation where they
get to amass a bunch of power and money
yeah we've already had that conversation
and we're two people right imagine if
there's 10,000 of us having that
conversation we're not silent people not
being like that's never gonna happen Shh
we're not gonna do that it's like yeah
there's sociopaths what do we do about
that yeah and people are just shitty in
general like if people can get an
advantage over other people then that's
typically what they do and most people
don't really investigate their beliefs
or the way that they interact they just
kind of go from situation to situation
and they just do whatever kind of feels
right to them which typically doesn't
have much consideration for the people
that they're coming into contact with
yeah well I mean I like the sound of
these ideas I'm interested in sort of
being part of the group of collective
people who are trying to solve these
problems and hopefully participate in
the ways that I can participate to it
because with the community that we've
both apart of there's a lot of different
ideas out there so what I'm hoping is
that we all sort of coalesce in a bunch
of different areas and we can kind of
you know
yeah so I think I really like on
bringing
what is the essence of the idea cafe -
game be like I think that is one of the
best things I have to offer is like I've
thought of how we have a conversation
with hundreds and thousands of people
it's not any way because any way that
happens is in my head and not on paper
so until we're using it oh crap that was
wrong how do we improve it how do we
improve that right that's why I'm not
putting in because I don't have it but
I'm not playing in tens of thousands
hundreds of thousands of dollars
to create the idea cafe before we've
held idea cafes we want to know what the
the issues are and know how to hold the
World Cafe online which is what it's
modeled after if anyone wants to look at
World Cafe I'm not gonna actually like
it right now but creating like to be
able to have our game be conversations
which are people all over the globe
wanting to have a say and like hey hey
how what are the questions we want to
answer together how do we have those
conversations how do we get people to
the table and have an effective
conversation with hundreds of people
I think it's breaking off into smaller
groups and also keep having
conversations repeatedly with a bunch of
people as often as possible in a way
that works which i think is what i
proposed is six different time slots
throughout the day so that one of them
works for you there every four hours so
one of them works for you and one or two
of them are horrible you'll never come
to them I'm never coming to the 2:00
a.m. one in my time zone unless I could
be awake at that time period yeah if you
can't get to sleep just have a have an
interesting conversation that's yeah I
yeah I'm I'm hopeful for you know the
development of this and I guess this is
sort of the first part of it so early
early days but yeah this helps like have
you coming and having a conversation and
having someone ask questions and
explaining them as opposed to me needing
to like in the back of my mind think of
all of those questions and just spew
them all out without finishing one and
it start you know name it like it's this
helps by ATD brain explain it yeah I
think it is true to some extent that
people think through conversation so
yeah I think that this is thus a good
way to go but I mean I'm not much man
interviewer obvious
conversation it's like ask you two
questions and answering and then you
know generates a new question that might
not be one that's written down and then
you know it sparks that I know I can't
write this all down in a coherent way
and I can answer questions on it all day
every day it's like alright that's what
I'm gonna do I'm just gonna figure out
and that is if we create the
conversational platform for game B using
zoom using existing technology I'm gonna
come and be part of those conversations
and maybe the global cooperative never
happens but pieces of it we'll get into
it right like it's about like okay if we
create something better together I'm not
holding strongly on to this one but I'm
bringing democracy I'm bringing
transparency I'm bringing like the power
of tech that we all own together and
showing up as unique individual and not
having to like I don't know give
ourselves over to the group I think
there's a lot of cost that comes with
that and those trade-offs have existed
before we have the technology we no
longer need those trade offs you don't
need to give yourself up to the group
because there's a group out there that
will accept you for you I think I think
everyone's got a lot of value within
them somewhere they just need to find a
way to unlock it hopefully we can figure
that out and yeah obviously there'll be
a lot of things that we're gonna come
across in order to solve but you know if
you get people who are passionate about
something you can bring them all
together and they'll figure it out no
crowd sourcing solutions is a good way
to go they're not gatekeeping but I mean
there'll be a lot of trouble with you
know coordination and cooperation just
because a lot of people are gonna have
conflicting ideas and maybe they can
just like work on separate things
hopefully we there's an efficiency that
we can figure out yeah yeah I mean I
think what I'm proposing is not the way
but but like it's a foundation of Ka'bah
I'm having like a conversation every
four hours it's in the car but you know
zoom coffee shop then you can just show
up you know when people will be in there
because it's kind of dissipated aren't
really people in there nobody know they
can show up and then I would like it to
be around a question because I think
that therefore I don't feel I have to
meet everything
the one right I don't have to get to air
all six conversations I only have to
show up to one or two because I'm just
gonna be part of a few conversations in
smaller groups and then how I envisioned
it and how I proposed it is that we do
like Monday Tuesday there's one question
and so come on at ones time period
during that day you have 48 hours to
answer the question then on on Wednesday
we harvest that conversation anyone that
was part of it can come on and one of
the one of the time periods and say how
that was for you what was generated what
came out of it how do we actually use
that information and maybe that doesn't
work for the first few questions because
we're more Debian to know each other and
getting since figure out like what we're
doing and what it is and then we repeat
that process in the next three days and
the seventh day we rest no the seventh
day we generate questions of like how do
we move this forward the next week right
what are questions they would we want to
show up an answer that would be powerful
to get into together and so I think
that's a way to have a conversation with
a large group of people globally right
and then eventually projects come out of
it and we break off into smaller groups
if we want to a need to write like the
idea is to is to just have fun playing
with game being like get to figure out
like what it is what could it be what
has it been but you know what I mean
like just having conversations that
everyone is invited to who game beatriz
in but nobody's in hierarchy because if
you don't get a show up to the table and
even me and be like I got all the
answers but I still only gonna take up a
quarter of the time and I mean offer my
solution to that topics question that's
it I don't get to say this is mine and
it has to be my way and neither does
anyone else even if they are first to
you know get into game B every note and
it is like sit at the table tell yours
tell your story tell your ideas yeah and
often these things have sort of an
organic structure to them anyway so
maybe just putting your ideas out there
is what sparks something in somebody
else and then that the kind of the
domino effect rolls on and then
eventually you know something gets done
and it looks you know either very
similar to what you were envisioning or
quite different still does the same
thing that you were hoping it today but
yes always I think even me I'm the only
one working on and every time I put it
out there
I'm like that didn't work and then I
have to put it out there again in a new
way
beautiful is every time I can't wait
until there's like we're doing it with
game be it it's like oh yeah okay
the whole point is one person you're
never like even if you're the smartest
person in the world you sitting at a
table with three other coverage people
is gonna be smarter than just you
because before they're like I think
we're just better together as long as
there's some amount of cohesion and
we're not spending all of our time on
conflict resolution yeah yeah well yeah
sort of into the rib wisdom space at the
moment and they're really interested in
this collective intelligence idea so
they're trying to come up with psycho
technologies to you know facilitate
conversations that can kind of solve
problems and generate new forms of
information and things like that so
hopefully something interesting comes
over there it sounds a little bit do
they have anything do they have an idea
on how to actually do that besides as
someone had said on the Twitter which
was like I don't know I I was like our
robots vody and I'm very confused just
what you're talking about like no not
robots for what do you more like
correlating our information I'm like
okay I'm okay with that but not if
they're then making decisions based on
what we've put into the system
no because AI kid like I'm like there's
so many ways but it's not showing up you
should can't really be gamed no I think
I think that's a thing that's a slightly
different thing know that these people
are dude like there's no AI or anything
like that it's just how do we have
conversations that are generative and
sort of you know a game the kind of
thing that can potentially out-compete
game a structures how do we think
collectively and really maximize the
intelligence of a crowd of people and
like what what are the ways that you can
have the conversation what are the
things to look out for like um one of
the ideas that's put out there as a kind
of a practice or a principle that people
can use is rule Omega so the idea of
rule Omega is when someone sees
something that at first comes across as
stupid or
not very well-thought-out rule Omega and
suggest that you should just assume that
you haven't if it sounds obvious it
sounds stupid then it just assumed that
you haven't quite understood what they
were saying that they haven't like quite
explained it in a way that's you know
resonates with you and then so just ask
questions and try to win busy to get
there and unravel that and so yeah I
mean I think that's generally a good
idea although I might my criticism there
would be you'd have to sort of
demonstrate that you were able to
generate ideas that were interesting or
maybe any kind of sense in the first
place because a lot of people just say
nonsense and it's like well you know if
they just say nonsense all the time the
chances are investigating that this
probably if you put an idea out there it
can absolutely be critiqued and people
are gonna ask questions yeah that's not
you know what I hope that's not break
you know make a rule like I hope it's
not cuz it's like what about because it
is being curious well what about this it
breaks down because of this what about
this what about this that's hopefully
making it better and if it makes it fall
apart it kind of was supposed to fall
apart exactly exactly well it's kind of
just the Socratic method like and I
think that's yeah just it's always a
good way to learn more about what other
people know and - what about what you
know because you know we as people were
very fallible in the way that we think
about things we have all these biases
that just bad like there's no there's no
formal training on how to think
logically within our education systems
at the moment so you know there's a lot
of their stuff that we have to work
through by ourselves and in groups so I
think those technologies and and they've
got other things like circling which I'm
still a little bit sort of vague about
as a concept but yeah the thing that was
posted on circling so confusing however
if you go to the website on circling
there's like a free two-hour seminar
thing that made sense then walk through
act you do a circling and I think he
does he does it with a woman like uh
eggs the the podcast that was talking
about circling I'm like what is to get
it I'm like I get it that's kind of like
they were told cafe to but like
I was I was quite confused because yeah
we're having a zoom call tomorrow in the
morning about it like I don't know what
this is but but yeah I mean it I think
there was another one that the lady was
talking about which reverse bowling
dialogue not sure if I'm saying that
right but just the idea is just kind of
you just say what's coming to your mind
and you just respond as off but
authentically as you can and throughout
the conversation which well I think one
of the interesting ideas or interesting
ways that this can go is just opening up
people's ability to be honest and to be
critical because I think there is always
a filter when you're having a dialogue
with people and yeah I wonder how much
that actually negatively impacts you
know the long-term outcome of
conversations because obviously it hurts
to hear things that are kind of critical
and sometimes harsh but you know like I
always have those critical thing
thoughts in my head and they're kind of
a tool for me to refine my own thinking
and sort of check myself so some people
haven't developed those things maybe
it's a good idea to you know bring that
into their mind space not to not to
bring them down but to give them a bit
more critical structure and because
because I think part of the benefits of
thinking as a collective being able to
implement the tools that you already use
yourself is sort of openly as you do
with your with your own person who knows
not recorded on YouTube because I'm
posting this so that it's it's on this
site so I'm gonna end this here and then
I wouldn't ask all right bye people
ciao sorry alright